{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>A coup began in this country because a leader had a gay son, Gustavo, and a drug addict son</em> <em>named Freddie</em>. The \"Archives of Terror\" were found in this country, which featured a coup led by Andres Rodriguez. This country was led for 35 years by one man, second to Cuba among Latin American countries in that regard. It was where the exiled Juan Peron and Anastasio Somoza fled to. For 10 points, name this South American country led by Alfredo Stroessner.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Paraguay</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>During this war, Louis Howe was targeted for badmouthing Josephus Daniels</em>. A drawing made in this war shows a slobbering ape monster carrying a club reading \"cultur.\" \"Four Minute Men\" were very active during this war, promoting the propaganda aims of the Creel Committee. During this war, \"liberty cabbage\" replaced \"sauerkraut\" in the American language. For 10 points, name this conflict during which the Espionage Act of 1917 was passed.", "answer": "<b><u>World War I</u></b> [or the <b><u>First World War</u></b>; prompt on the <b><u>Great War</u></b>]", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>An author of this first name claimed that the Britons were descended from a great-grandson of</em> <em>Aeneas named Brutus.</em> This was the first name of the author of <em>Historia Regum Britanniae</em>, who hailed from Monmouth. This is the first name of an author whose most famous work opens with the narrator entering The Tabard and meeting pilgrims such as the Wife of Bath. For 10 points, give this first name of the author of the <em>Canterbury Tales</em>, whose last name was Chaucer.", "answer": "<b><u>Geoffrey</u></b> [or <b><u>Geoffrey</u></b> of Monmouth; or <b><u>Geoffrey</u></b> Chaucer; do not accept or prompt on \"Chaucer\" or \"Monmouth\"]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>With William Monroe Trotter, this scholar convened a meeting near Ontario to discuss his</em> <em>people's uplift in 1905.</em> This man theorized a \"sense of always looking at one's self through the eyes of others\" called \"double consciousness.\" This Massachusetts-raised, Harvard-educated sociologist helped start the Niagara movement, a precursor to the NAACP. For 10 points, name this black academic who argued for immediate legal equality and wrote <em>The Souls of Black Folk</em>.", "answer": "William Edward Burghard <b><u>DuBois</u></b> (\"due\" \"BOYZ\", but accept pronunciation like doo BWAH)  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>Harry Truman claimed this man was \"one of those counterfeits\" after this person talked to the</em> <em>press about a private meeting</em>. This man was heard on tape agreeing with his friend Richard Nixon regarding the Jewish \"stranglehold\" of the media. He began a radio show called the <em>Hour</em> <em>of Decision</em> that featured testimonies. This man's son, Franklin, is head of the relief organization Samaritan's Purse. For 10 points, name this Christian leader noted for his evangelical crusades.", "answer": "William \"Billy\" <b><u>Graham</u></b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<em>This man first gained controversy after defending the consumption of sausages during Lent.</em> After marrying Anna Reinhard, this man led a petition to abolish celibacy from the clergy. This man was killed during the Kappel Wars, which started when an alliance of Forest Cantons was formed against him. At the Marburg Colloquy, this man argued with Martin Luther over the nature of the Eucharist. For 10 points, name this Swiss Reformation leader from Zurich.", "answer": "Huldrych <b><u>Zwingli</u></b> [or Ulrich <b><u>Zwingli</u></b>] {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This man played right guard on Fordham's \"Seven Blocks of Granite\" offensive line</em>. In a playoff game, this man said it \"Run it! And let's get the hell out of here!\" to his quarterback. President Kennedy once personally asked this man to \"come back\" to coaching Army's team. With quarterback Bart Starr, this head coach won the \"Ice Bowl\" and the first two Super Bowls. For 10 points, name this Green Bay Packers coach who is the namesake of the Super Bowl trophy.", "answer": "Vincent \u201cVince\u201d <b><u>Lombardi</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This ruler unusually destroyed the city of Mari instead of capturing it.</em> This king fought many battles against Rim Sin I of Larsa, although the two allied together to defeat invading Elamites. His son Samsu-Iluna was unable to keep the lands this king conquered. This son of Sin-Muballit names a set of two hundred and eighty two decrees, including punishments based on \"an eye for an eye.\" For 10 points, name this Babylonian king who is best known for his law code.", "answer": "<b><u>Hammurabi</u></b> [or <b><u>Ammurapi</u></b>; or <b><u>Khammurabi</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>One side in this battle fell into disarray after a rumor spread that loot taken from Bordeaux</em> <em>had been stolen.</em> This battle was preceded by another in which Odo the Great was soundly defeated near the Garonne River. A failed cavalry charge up a hill to attack a phalanx formation was repeatedly attempted by the losers in this battle, who were led by Abd ar-Rahman. For 10 points, name this battle won by Charles Martel, in which his forces halted Muslim expansion in Europe.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Tours</u></b> [or Battle of <b><u>Poitiers</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>Wilson Goode was the first African-American mayor of this city</em>. This city was home to a radical group founded by John Africa named MOVE, which was bombed by this city\u2019s police force. In 2010, a museum partially dedicated to George Washington\u2019s slaves opened in this city. Police officer Daniel Faulkner was allegedly shot in this city by Mumia Abu-Jamal, whose mayors have included Ed Rendell and Michael Nutter. For 10 points, name this largest city in Pennsylvania.", "answer": "<b><u>Philadelphia</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "BA"}, {"question": "<em>In this fictional work, a professor declares on TV that \"</em>God<em> exists, and he's American\" after a</em> <em>1959 atomic energy accident</em>. In this work, Richard Nixon is in his 5th term as president after the Americans won the Vietnam War by using the blue-skinned Dr. Manhattan. It is set in a timeline in which costumed heroes were real outside comic books. For 10 points, name this graphic novel in which Dave Gibbons and Alan Moore introduced the masked detective Rorschach.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Watchmen</u> </b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Months after this event, a protest called the Golaniad erupted against the FSN.</em> This event began with resistance to the eviction of pastor Laszlo Tokes (<b>pr. LAZ-low TOAK-esh</b>). A leader tried to end this event with a speech from his balcony, but had to flee in a helicopter instead. This event began in Timisoara and ended with the show trial and execution of its target and his wife, Elena. For 10 points, name this revolution which toppled the government of Nicolae Ceausescu (<b>pr. cho-CHESS-koo) </b>in Bucharest.", "answer": "<b><u>Romania</u></b>n <b><u>Revolution</u></b> of 1989 [or <b><u>overthrow</u></b> of Nicolae <b><u>Ceausescu</u></b> before \"Nicolae\" is read; or obvious equivalents]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In this document, Edwin Montagu replaced the word \u201cthat\u201d with \u201cin.\u201d</em> despite not supporting it. Winston Churchill\u2019s 1922 White Paper sought to clarify this document, which Lord Curzon supported. It was adopted into the Treaty of Sevres partially resulted from the influence of Chaim Weizmann. For 10 points, name this document written by a Foreign Secretary addressed to Baron Rothschild which professed British support for Palestine becoming a Jewish Homeland.", "answer": "<b><u>Balfour Declaration</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Urban legends state that this substance was used to create temporary tattoos in the shape of</em> <em>blue stars.</em> This substance was first produced by Albert Hofmann. As depicted by Tom Wolfe, Ken Kesey combined this substance with Kool-Aid. This substance was used in CIA-led mind control experiments called Project MK Ultra. The use of this drug, which is similar to psilocybin, was encouraged by Timothy Leary. For 10 points, name this hallucinogen informally called \"acid.\"", "answer": "<b><u>LSD</u></b> [or <b><u>lysergic acid diethylamide</u></b>; or <b><u>acid</u></b> until it is read]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>One holder of this position, Luther Terry, issued a 1964 report that ultimately led to</em> <em>commercials featuring the Magnificent Seven theme song being pulled from the air</em>. Jocelyn Elders was criticized by conservatives while holding this post during the Clinton Administration. While holding this post, C. Everett Koop mailed information on AIDS to every household. For 10 points, name this public health position of the federal government whose namesake warning began appearing on cigarette packages in 1965.", "answer": "<b><u>Surgeon General</u></b> of the United States", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This person lost a battle to an army which used the \u201cTwin Sisters\u201d cannons</em>. This person was removed from power for the last time by the Plan of Ayutla, and his fake leg was lost at the Battle of Cerro Gordo. This loser at the Battle of San Jacinto ordered the Goliad massacre as well as an attack on a location defended by Davy Crockett, the Alamo. For 10 points, name this President of Mexico who lost the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "Antonio Lopez de <b><u>Santa Anna</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This person built the \u201cPortus\u201d north of Ostia</em>. This person affirmed the rights of Jews in the Letter to the Alexandrians. This husband of Messalina was served by the freedman Narcissus and was tutored by the historian Livy. He came to power when the Praetorian Guard found him hiding behind a curtain, and he was killed by poisoned food prepared by his wife, Agrippina. For 10 points, name this successor to Caligula and subject of a Robert Graves novel.", "answer": "Tiberius <b><u>Claudius</u></b> Caesar Augustus Germanicus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The ILLIAC I computer was used to calculate the trajectory of this object.</em> Construction on this object began after a similar project named Object D was delayed. Response to this object's appearance led to the creation of Project Vanguard, which had the same aim. The launching of this object triggered the Space Race between the United States and its creators, the Soviet Union. For 10 points, name this first satellite launched into space.", "answer": "<b><u>Sputnik</u></b> 1", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This event was sparked by a requirement that debts be paid in specie rather than paper money</em>. Governor James Bowdoin called up the state militia during this event following the closure of the court at Northampton.This event\u2019s namesake was defeated by General Benjamin Lincoln at Petersham after a failed attempt to seize the Springfield arsenal. For 10 points, name this 1786 to 1787 rebellion in Massachusetts that contributed to the demise of the Articles of Confederation.", "answer": "<b><u>Shays\u2019 or Shays\u2019s</u></b> Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In 1993, this building was the target of a car bomb set by members of Cosa Nostra.</em> This building was first made public by Grand Duke Peter Leopold of Lorraine. A corridor links this building to the Pitti Palace. This building was originally constructed as an administrative center for Cosimo de Medici, but now houses artworks such as Botticelli's <em>The Birth of Venus</em>. For 10 points, name this art museum located in Florence.", "answer": "<b><u>Uffizi</u></b> Gallery [or Galleria degli <b><u>Uffizi</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In response to this bill, Thomas Jefferson described it as a \"fire bell in the night\" that</u></b></em> <em><b><u>would be the \"knell of the Union.\"</u> </b></em><b><u>Jesse B. Thomas added an important amendment to this</u></b> <b><u>bill. The Tallmadge Amendment was submitted prior to this agreement and would have</u></b> <b><u>achieved the (+)</u>opposite result. This agreement took land that was formerly part of Massachusetts andcreated the new state of</b> (*) Maine. Later ruled unconstitutional in the <em>Dred</em> <em>Scott</em> case, it established a line at the 36 degrees, 30 minutes parallel. For 10 points, name this bill that admitted a new Midwest slave state to the Union with many conditions.", "answer": "<b><u>Missouri Compromise</u></b> of 1820 (accept <b><u>Compromise of 1820</u></b>)  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A monument commemorating this battle consists of the world's largest doric column.</u> </b></em><b><u>The</u></b> <b><u>winning commander here and four others escaped gunfire while in a rowboat after the</u></b> <b><u>Lawrence sunk. The turning point of this battle came when the</u> </b><em><b><u>Detroit</u></b></em><b><u> collided with the (+)</u> </b><em><b>Queen Charlotte</b></em><b>. A flagship in this battle carried a banner with the message \"Don't give up the ship.\" This battle led to the pronouncement \"we have (*)</b> met the enemy and they are ours\" by Oliver Hazard Perry. For 10 points, name this naval engagement in the War of 1812, which was fought on one of the Great Lakes.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Lake Erie</u></b> [or Battle of <b><u>Put-in-Bay</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>T<b><u>he \u201cTiger\u201d battalion of Massachusetts claimed to have written one version of this song\u2019s</u></b></em> <em><b><u>lyrics.</u> </b></em><b><u>This song has its roots in the camp meeting hymn \u201cSay, Brothers, Will You Meet Us?\u201d</u></b> <b><u>It was sung by mourners at Winston Churchill\u2019s funeral, and the union anthem \u201cSolidarity</u></b> <b><u>Forever\u201d also uses its melody. One version (+)</u>of the lyrics to this song states that its namesake (*)</b> abolitionist\u2019s \u201cbody lies a-mouldering in the grave\u201d but \u201chis soul\u2019s a-marching on.\u201d For 10 points, Julia Ward Howe wrote new lyrics for what Civil War tune also known as \u201cJohn Brown\u2019s Body\u201d?", "answer": "\u201c<b><u>Battle Hymn Of The Republic</u></b>\u201d [or \u201c<b><u>John Brown\u2019s Body</u></b>\u201d before mention]  {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This economist's ideas were revived in</u> </b></em><b><u>The Production of Commodities by the Means of</u></b> <b><u>Commodities</u> </b><em><b><u>by Piero Sraffa.</u> </b></em><b><u>This economist described how differences in land fertility can</u></b> <b><u>lead to differing prices in (+)</u>rent for those lands. This economist criticized the Corn Laws by discussing how they would cause an increase in rent. In </b><em><b>On the Principles of </b></em><b>(*)</b><em> Political</em> <em>Economy and Taxation</em>, this man laid out a system in which free trade can mutually benefit two countries. For 10 points, name this British economist best known for his law of comparative advantage and the law of iron wages.", "answer": "David <b><u>Ricardo</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Two attempts were made to capture this city's Fort Wagner, the second of which led to the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>death of Robert Gould Shaw.</u></b></em><b><u> The U.S.S. Housatonic was blockading this city when the H.L.</u></b> <b><u>Hunley sank it. A slave in this city named Telemaque won the lottery and bought his own</u></b> <b><u>freedom with the money. Despite not being near a (+)</u>plate boundary, this city was hit by a devastating earthquake in 1886. Denmark Vesey attempted to launch a (*)</b> slave revolt in this city. The first shots of the American Civil War were fired at this city's Fort Sumter. For 10 points, name this port city in South Carolina.", "answer": "<b><u>Charleston</u></b>, South Carolina  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This island is where Operation Claret, part of an undeclared war known as the Konfrontasi,</u></b></em> <em><b><u>took place.</u></b></em><b><u> A kingdom on this island was ruled by the Brooke family, who were nicknamed</u></b> <b><u>the White Rajahs. The northeastern part of this island was once owned by the Sultanate of</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u>Sulu, but is now part of the state of Sabah. A small oil-rich country on this island is ruled by (*)</b> Hassanal Bolkiah as a sultanate. Sarawak and Kalimantan are regions of this third-largest island in the world. For 10 points, name this island shared by Malaysia, Indonesia, and Brunei.", "answer": "<b><u>Borneo</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This team scored five goals in the third period of the \"Good Friday Massacre.\"</u></b></em><b><u> Forty-seven</u></b> <b><u>police cars were destroyed following this team's 1993 Stanley Cup victory over the Los</u></b> <b><u>Angeles Kings. In 1955, this team forfeited a game to the Detroit Red Wings when a tear</u></b> <b><u>gas bomb exploded during (+)</u>fan protests over Clarence Campbell's decision to suspend this team's starplayer (*)</b>, Maurice Richard (<b>pr. ree-SHARD</b>). For 10 points, what team with more Stanley Cup victories than any other is the only current NHL team whose official name is in French?", "answer": "Montreal <b><u>Canadiens</u></b> [or <b><u>Montreal</u></b> Canadiens; or Les <b><u>Canadiens</u></b> de Montreal; or Le <b><u>Club de Hockey</u><u>Canadien</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>An incident at this place started when Troy Canty asked a man for money.</u></b></em><b><u> A local theory</u></b> <b><u>states that, historically, the cost to get into this place has matched the price of a slice of</u></b> <b><u>pizza. Stanley Milgram set up an experiment about breaching social norms in this place.</u></b> <b><u>This place is where Bernhard (+)</u>Goetz (</b>pr. GETS<b>) shot four African-American men in 1984. In late 2014, Dr. Craig Spencer unwisely used this system after being (*)</b> exposed to the Ebola virus. For 10 points, name this underground system that takes commuters through the Big Apple.", "answer": "<b><u>New York</u></b> City <b><u>Subway</u></b> [or <b><u>NY</u></b>C <b><u>Subway</u></b>; prompt on partial answer]  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>An unsuccessful siege of this non-French city may have inspired its bakers to invent the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>croissant.</u></b></em><b><u> Bags of coffee left behind by this city's attackers legendarily caused the</u></b> <b><u>establishment of many coffeehouses here. The Pummerin, a bell made from molten-down</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u>Ottoman cannons, is found at this city's St. Stephen's Cathedral. John III Sobieski led a charge of (*)</b> Winged Hussars during a defeat for Kara Mustafa Pasha here. Suleiman the Magnificent's conquest of Europe was stopped at this city. For 10 points, name this city from which the Habsburgs ruled central Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Vienna</u></b>, Austria  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Daily Sketch reporter Paul Guihard was murdered at this university</u></b></em><b><u>. This university's</u></b> <b><u>\"ghosts\" were the subject of a Wright Thompson article from 2010. Governor Theodore</u></b> <b><u>Bilbo tried to move this university during the 1930's, while Governor Ross (+)</u>Barnett was held in contempt for his later actions regarding this college. Students in a dorm here bounced basketballs all night above the room of adespised fellow student, James</b> (*) Meredith, who attempted to integrate this university in 1962. For 10 points, name this Southern university located in a city named Oxford.", "answer": "University of <b><u>Mississippi</u></b> [or <b><u>Ole Miss</u></b>; do not accept \u201cMississippi State\u201d]  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This kingdom joined a coalition against Napoleon with the Treaty of Kalisz (</u></b><u>pr.</u><u>kah-lish</u><b><u>).</u> </b></em><b><u>With Leopold II, a ruler of this kingdom agreed to intervene in France if Louis XVI was</u></b> <b><u>threatened by signing the Declaration of (+)</u> Pillnitz. The French later defeated this kingdom's forces at Valmy. Another ruler of this kingdom disregarded the (*)</b> Pragmatic Sanction, triggering the War of the Austrian Succession. For 10 points, name this kingdom ruled by the Hohenzollern dynasty, whose territory became much of modern-day Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Prussia</u></b> [or <b><u>Preussen</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}], "bonuses": []}